Hello everybody. Today's
דף *daf* is דף י׳ *Daf Yud*, and we're up to שבועות
Shavuos, *Shavuot*, and we pick up with our... we're way ahead, we'll
get you out of here early today. We pick up about twelve
lines down at the two dots. ר׳ מאיר אומר כל שעירי כפרתן
שוה *Rabbi Meir omer kol seirei kapparotan shaveh*. Okay, so we had
this whole breakdown here and now ר׳ מאיר *Rabbi Meir* says all
the goats, but he doesn't mean all, he means only the מוסף
musaf. *Musaf*. So all of the goats, meaning from this point on,
יום כיפור Yom Kippur, *Yom Kippur*, מוסף musaf, *Musaf*, רגלים regalim *Regalim*,
ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh? *Rosh Chodesh*, they're all doing the same work.
He seems to basically buy into ר׳ שמעון *Rabbi Shimon*'s idea that
ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh *Rosh Chodesh* does, or that they all do
now, because they're all doing the same work. The eating of a
קרבן korban, טמא tamei *Korban Tamei*, the רגלים regalim *Regalim* do, you
know, whatever. Okay, let me not say it that way. There's an
eating of a קרבן korban, טמא *Korban Tamei* that's not knowing at
the beginning at the end. There's not knowing at the beginning and
knowing at the end. We've divided them into these three. ר׳ מאיר
*Rabbi Meir* says they're all doing, they all work on all three
of them. Okay, so let's take a look at the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara*. אמר ר׳ חמא בר ר׳ חנינא *Amar Rabbi Chama bar Rabbi
Chanina*, מאי טעמא דר׳ מאיר *mai ta'ama de'Rabbi Meir*, what's the reasoning
of ר׳ מאיר *Rabbi Meir*? אמר קרא Amar kra, ושעיר u'se'ir ושעיר
u'se'ir. *Amar Kra v'Seir v'Seir*. When it speaks about, you know, again,
that extra ו׳ *vav* by the ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh. ושעיר עזים
אחד לחטאת לכפר *Rosh Chodesh v'Seir izim echad l'chatat l'chapair*.
So anyway, that ו׳ *vav* is הוקשו כל השעירים זה לזה *hukshu
kol ha'seirim zeh l'zeh*.
ו׳ מוסיף על ענין ראשון *Vav mosif al inyan rishon*. So if
you take a look, right, you know, in where it mentions all
of the שעירי *seirei*,
which is in פנחס Pinchas, במדבר כ״ח *Pinchas Bamidbar Chaf-Chet*, right, but
it's all of the מוספים musafim, *Musafim*, I should say. So there,
it's if you just look at the end of each one of
these, right, I mean every almost every single one ends in the
same way. You have שבת Shabbos, *Shabbat*, then you've got ראש חודש
Rosh Chodesh, ושעיר עזים אחד לחטאת לה׳ *Rosh Chodesh v'Seir izim echad
l'chatat l'Hashem*. That's the לחטאת לה׳ *l'chatat l'Hashem*. Right? Then you have
פסח Pesach? *Pesach* and it's ושעיר חטאת chatat, אחד *u'Seir chatat echad*.
ושעיר *u'Seir*, right? And then you've got now, of course, then you
have שבועות Shavuos *Shavuot*, which is שעיר se'ir עזים *Seir izim* without
the ו׳ *vav*. So we're going to get to that, right? But
then you've got ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah, ושעיר עזים אחד חטאת chatat?
לכפר *Rosh Hashanah u'Seir izim echad chatat l'chapair*. Then you have, you
know, יום כיפור Yom Kippur, *Yom Kippur*. יום כיפור Yom Kippur? *Yom
Kippur* doesn't have the ו׳ *vav*. שעיר se'ir עזים אחד *Seir izim
echad*. Then you have סוכות Succos ושעיר עזים אחד חטאת chatat. *Sukkot
u'Seir izim echad chatat*. Okay, and then all the days of סוכות
Succos *Sukkot*, ושעיר ושעיר ושעיר ושעיר ושעיר ושעיר ושעיר *u'Seir u'Seir u'Seir
u'Seir u'Seir u'Seir u'Seir*. So other than שבועות *Shavuot* and יום כיפור
Yom Kippur, *Yom Kippur*, everything has a ו׳ *vav*. So because everything
has a ו׳ *vav*, so remember included in that list there in
פנחס Pinchas, *Pinchas* is יום כיפור מוסף Yom Kippur Musaf, *Yom Kippur
Musaf*. So since all of these, well יום כיפור מוסף Yom Kippur
Musaf. *Yom Kippur Musaf* itself doesn't have a ו׳ *vav*, we'll get
to this, but since basically we start with the idea that we've
identified these different things that we did yesterday with ר׳ שמעון *Rabbi
Shimon*, so we start with, you know, a קרבן korban טמא *Korban
Tamei* for ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh, *Rosh Chodesh*, not knowing beginning at
the end for the רגלים regalim. *Regalim*, and knowing at the end
and not at the beginning for יום כיפור מוסף yom kippur musaf
*Yom Kippur Musaf*. And the fact that all of the קרבנות korbanos,
*Korbanot* here have a ו׳ *vav*, it links everything to one another
and it basically says everything one does, the other thing does. Okay.
So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says ו׳ מוסיף על ענין ראשון *Vav
mosif al inyan rishon*. Now קסלקא דעתך דכל חד מחד גמר *kasalka
da'itach de'kol chad m'chad gmar*. So we assumed that everything was learning
from everything else, meaning it's basically, or from the thing that was
next with...
if you stop it without the ו׳ *vav*, I understand.
Anyway, so we're linking all of these together. Okay, that's what we're
doing now. Now כל חד מחד גמר *kol chad m'chad gmar* means
that you basically have,
right, here's ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh *Rosh Chodesh*, and then was פסח
*Pesach*, and then was שבועות *Shavuot*, we're going to get to the
פרשת שבועות *parashat Shavuot* doesn't have a ו׳ *vav* in a minute,
then was ראש השנה *Rosh Hashanah*, then was יום כיפור Yom Kippur
*Yom Kippur*, then was סוכות Sukkot? *Sukkot*. Okay, now this one basically
we say is
קרבן korban טמא *Korban Tamei*, right?
יום כיפור Yom Kippur
*Yom Kippur* we say is basically ידיעה yedi'ah, בסוף *yediah basof*. And
all of these is like no ידיעה *yediah* at all.
But for יום
כיפור Yom
Kippur
*Yom Kippur* there's a bunch of them, there's בפנים bifnim, *bifnim* and
then there's...
yeah, well no, we're only doing the מוספים musafim *Musafim*, okay, only
what's mentioned here in פנחס Pinchas. *Pinchas*, like I said, that's why
my line is down here. Okay, so כל חד מחד גמר *kol
chad m'chad gmar* means you learn סוכות *Sukkot* from יום כיפור Yom
Kippur. *Yom Kippur*, you learn יום כיפור Yom Kippur. *Yom Kippur* from
ראש השנה *Rosh Hashanah*, you know, sort of like each one like
you just exchange with the other one. Okay. You got that? So
that's כל חד מחד גמר *kol chad m'chad gmar*. So now here's
a question. How are you going to get, for example, the קרבן
korban, טמא *Korban Tamei* from ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh. *Rosh Chodesh* all
the way down here to סוכות *Sukkot*? Right, so well cause it's,
you know, it's like a wave. Okay. So once you learn פסח
*Pesach* from ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh *Rosh Chodesh*, and שבועות *Shavuot* from
פסח *Pesach*, and ראש השנה *Rosh Hashanah* from שבועות *Shavuot*, and יום
כיפור Yom Kippur *Yom Kippur* from that and that and that, eventually
you will get, right, the קרבן korban טמא *Korban Tamei* down here
to סוכות *Sukkot*. How do you get ידיעה בסוף up there at
ראש חודש? Rosh Chodesh Same way, right? Ta da da da da,
okay? So by constantly connecting them in a chain, okay, and one
learns from the other, you get everything working for everything else. Okay,
wait. I will worry about that, Michael. But first the גמרא Gemara
has another
question. כסלקא דעתך כולהו מהדדי גמרי. Kasalka daitach kuleihu me-hadadi gamrei. Okay,
הא אמר רבי יוחנן כל התורה כולה למדים למד מלמד מלמד
מלמד חוץ מקדשים. Ha amar Rabbi Yochanan kol haTorah kulah lemedim lamed
mi-lamad mi-lamad mi-lamad chutz mi-kodshim. In the entire תורה Torah you can
derive one הלכה, halacha, you can derive something from a derived הלכה.
halacha. Okay,
B can learn from A and C can learn from B what
B learned from A. That, okay, that's למד מלמד, lamed mi-lamed, that
you can learn something that was learned from somewhere else, you can
learn a derived הלכה halacha and apply it to somewhere else. Okay,
חוץ מקדשים, chutz mi-kodshim, except for קרבנות, korbanot okay, שאין למדים למד
מלמד מלמד מלמד. she'ein lemedim lamed mi-lamad mi-lamad mi-lamad. You cannot learn
something, a derived הלכה halacha from another, you cannot derive a הלכה
halacha from a derived הלכה. halacha. All right? So therefore, you can't
get ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh to go all the way down or
סוכות to go all the way up. Once it was derived, it
can't go somewhere else. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says הא
לא קשיא. ha lo kashya. That's not difficult. כולהו מהכא גמרי. kuleihu
me-hacha gamrei. Okay, now, so fine, so basically it says no, no,
this is not the way it works. It doesn't work like this.
That wouldn't happen. It goes direct. Okay, because of the ו, vav,
although this is what's juxtaposed to it in the פסוקים, pesukim, okay,
but somehow because the ו vav links them, you're allowed to go
direct. So סוכות goes direct to here. Here it says ושעיר and
here it says ושעיר. So, we don't have to go through that,
we can go directly from ראש חודש. Rosh Chodesh. ראש חודש, Rosh
Chodesh. and ראש חודש, Rosh Chodesh? you know, can basically learn directly
from יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, okay? So basically, גזירה שוה, gezeirah
shavah, is that another way of saying that?
Yes, I guess. I mean, it's true. It's not by the juxtaposition.
Since they've all got ו vavs and since they're all in the
same פרשה, parsha, you can connect any one to any other one.
Okay, so you don't have to do it through a ripple effect,
you can just go straight to the ones you want. So something
like שבועות, okay, that'll learn from ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh that it's
from a קרבן תמיד korban tamid and it'll learn from יום כיפור,
Yom Kippur, right, that it is for no ידיעה, whatever, and he
can teach whatever. No, it won't transfer what it learned, but the
point is is that you can do a hop. Okay, you don't
have to do it through going through the one that is right
next to you. You can go straight to any other one. So
if you're allowed to go straight to any other one, okay, then
that allows you to do it directly and not through derivative. Now
the גמרא Gemara gets to the question that was bothering Michael. Okay,
so the גמרא Gemara says תינח כל דכתיב ביה ושעיר. teinach kol
d'ketiv bei u'se'ir. Fine, it works for all the ones that it
has the ו. vav. עצרת ויום הכיפורים דלא כתיב ביה ושעיר מנלן?
Atzeret v'Yom HaKippurim d'lo ketiv bei u'se'ir minalan? How about עצרת, Atzeret,
how about שבועות and יום כיפור? Yom Kippur It doesn't have the
ו. vav. That should prevent you from sort of learning from the
other ones. Okay, so אלא, ella, fine, forget the whole ו vav
thing. אלא אמר רב יונה אמר קרא: ella amar Rav Yonah amar
kra: אלה תעשו לה' במועדיכם. eileh ta'asu l'Hashem b'mo'adeichem. This is, that's
how it ends at the end of all of the קרבנות korbanot
by in פנחס, this is what you should do on your holidays.
הוקשו כל המועדות כולם זה לזה. hukshu kol ha-mo'adot kulam zeh la-zeh.
That במועדיכם, b'mo'adeichem, the fact that it has a summary פסוק, pasuk,
that links them all together and that allows you to apply, all
right, that's the way it's being read. That allows you to assume
that the way any individual קרבן חטאת korban chatas functions by one
is the way it functions by others as well. But now the
גמרא Gemara has got another question. וראש חודש לאו מועד הוא? v'Rosh
Chodesh lav mo'ed hu? But one minute, במועדיכם b'mo'adeichem should not include
ראש חודש. Rosh Chodesh Okay, I mean the funny thing is that
even שבת, Shabbos I know, it's included in the פרשה parsha and
even שבת is included in the פרשה. parsha. Okay, so the גמרא
Gemara says איברא, ibra, yes, ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh. נמי איקרי מועד.
nami ikri mo'ed. ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh is called a מועד. mo'ed.
It's a little ironic because, what? But איברא, ibra, yes, in truth.
In truth ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh, is called a מועד, mo'ed, which
is actually funny because מועד mo'ed means an appointed day. And if
there's any day which is sort of one that we designate, right,
and that we do a job at setting the date, it's ראש
חודש. Rosh Chodesh, Everything else is a set date as a function
of ראש חודש. Rosh Chodesh, But anyway,
איברא ראש חודש נמי איקרי מועד דהא אמר אביי. ibra Rosh Chodesh
nami ikri mo'ed de-ha amar Abaye. דאמר אביי תמוז דהאי שתא מלויי
מליוהו. d'amar Abaye Tammuz d'hai shata miluyei malyuhi. The תמוז Tammuz of
the year when the, when the מרגלים Meraglim came back was a
full תמוז, Tammuz, which allowed that the crying that they did, the,
which allowed it to be that the מרגלים Meraglim came back on
the eighth of אב Av and the crying that they did was
on the ninth of אב Av and that that evening. And that's
why the ninth of אב Av was set as the day of
mourning for future generations. Had it been a normal, a normal year
where תמוז Tammuz would have been a twenty-nine-day month and not a
thirty-day month, then it would have been the tenth of אב. Av.
But God wanted to arrange, what what what?
I'm sorry, what were we talking about?
We're talking about in the time when the מרגלים Meraglim came back
in the מדבר. midbar.
Okay, the forty days that they went beforehand, okay, I got it.
Because from forty days we have an extra, from forty days, the
day that they returned, had the year been a normal year where
תמוז Tammuz was a twenty-nine-day month, they would have returned on the
ninth of אב. Av. and then the crying would have happened on
the tenth of אב. Av. But God wanted the day of crying
to be the ninth of אב, Av, that was designated to be
the day of mourning, and because God wanted the ninth of אב
Av to be the day of mourning, it worked out that תמוז
Tammuz was a full month. תמוז Tammuz is a month that precedes
אב. Av.
Did we assume they left on a ראש חודש? Rosh Chodesh.
I mean it could just... I don't understand what's bothering you. If
the month before is a day short or a day longer, it
affects whether you're showing up on the eighth or the ninth.
But we don't know when they left.
It doesn't matter when they left! Michael... Never mind, it's okay.
You're not understanding it.
Look. Here's תמוז. Tammuz. Twenty-nine, if it's twenty-nine days, right? Here's אב.
Av. Okay. They're coming back on this day. Correct. If... are we
going to call this day day eight or day nine? It depends
if we make ראש חודש אב Rosh Chodesh Av here or do
we make ראש חודש אב Rosh Chodesh Av here. Okay? Based on
when we make ראש חודש אב, Rosh Chodesh Av, this day will
either... if we make ראש חודש אב Rosh Chodesh Av here, this
day will be called day nine. If we make ראש חודש אב
Rosh Chodesh Av here, then that day will be called day eight.
Okay?
What we're saying is where did we begin the count?
I don't care where we begin the counting! They left forty days
ago! That's irrelevant! They are coming back on this day! Who the
heck cares how long they were gone? This is the day they
are coming back. Is this day the eighth of אב Av or
the ninth of אב? Av? Okay? It depends on whether this day
was ראש חודש אב Rosh Chodesh Av or that day was ראש
חודש אב. Rosh Chodesh Av. You guys will figure it out later.
I do not understand what the problem is, we're moving on. Okay,
so anyway, so the point is, is that they came back, the
way it worked out is that they came back on the eighth
of אב, Av, which meant that the night they cried was the
ninth of אב, Av, which is how... which is God wanted the
ninth of אב Av to be the night that was set for
mourning. But that was only because ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh, was a
day late. Okay? That allowed the day that they came back to
be called the eighth of אב. Av. It's just a question of
the label, the name you give the day. If ראש חודש Rosh
Chodesh had been
at the normal time, right, and the previous month had been a
twenty-nine day month, the day they came back would have been called
the ninth of אב Av and the crying would have been on
the tenth of אב. Av. So in order to make it that
the day they came back
was the eighth of אב Av and the crying was on the
ninth, God made the previous month a full month. Okay? תמוז דהאי
שתא מלויי מליוהי. Tammuz de-hai shata miluyei mulyuhi.
The תמוז Tammuz of that year was a full תמוז. Tammuz. דכתיב
De-chtiv קרא עלי מועד לשבור בחורי, kara alai moed lishbor bachurai,
and this is how we're using the word מועד moed with ראש
חודש. Rosh Chodesh Declare for me a מועד moed to cause the
shattering of my young ones, talking about like, you know, תשעה באב
Tisha B'Av and so on. But the idea was, was that it
was all sort of ordained. Not that God ordained that they would
sin, but God ordained it that the day that the crying would
happen that evening would be the ninth of אב. Av. And that
was a function of the fact that the previous month was a
full month. All right. So anyway, that just shows you that ראש
חודש Rosh Chodesh is called a מועד moed because אביי Abaye says
so. That's the proof. Okay. תשעה באב? Tisha B'Av?
I understand, but אביי Abaye is דורש darshening the פסוק pasuk this
way. That's how we know it. Anyway, moving on. That's how we
link all these things together, and we know for רבי מאיר Rabbi
Meir all these קרבנות korbanot do the same job. Okay.
אמר רבי יוחנן ומודה רבי מאיר בשעיר הנעשה בפנים שאינו מכפר כפרתן
והן אינן מכפרים כפרתו. Amar Rabbi Yochanan u-modeh Rabbi Meir be-sa'ir ha-na'aseh
bifnim she-eino mechaper kapartan ve-hein einan mechaperim kaparto. All that is good
by the מוספים, musafim because the מוספים musafim are all linked. But
by the goat that is done on the inside, you know, what's
there in אחרי מות, Acharei Mos, the center עבודה avodah of יום
כיפור, Yom Kippur that is... they don't do... neither of them does
each other's works. Okay? The מוספים musafs of the other days including
יום כיפור Yom Kippur doesn't do what the goat on the inside
of יום כיפור Yom Kippur does, and that goat doesn't do what
they
do. והוא אינו מכפר כפרתן. Ve-hu eino mechaper kapartan. The goat on
the inside doesn't do what the מוספים Musafim do. כפרה אחת מכפר
ואינו מכפר שתי כפרות. Kapara achas mechaper ve-eino mechaper shtei kaparos. It
says that it should be אחת, achas, right? We said that before
like אחת בשנה. achas bashana. Okay? One in the year, so it
only does one function, not multiple functions. הן אינן
מכפרים כפרתו, Hein einan mechaperim kaparto, and they don't do what it
does. אמר קרא אחת בשנה. Amar kra achas bashana. The juxtaposition of
the word אחת achas to the word שנה shana is telling you
this job that is done by the goat on יום כיפור Yom
Kippur on the inner... on the Holy of Holies, is only done
once in the year. Nothing else does its job. So it only
does one job, and nothing else does its job. כפרה זו לא
תהא אלא אחת בשנה. Kapara zu lo tehe ela achas bashana. Okay,
fine. תניא נמי הכי, Tanya nami hachi, it was taught similarly: על
שאין בה ידיעה לא בתחילה ולא בסוף ועל שאין בה ידיעה בתחילה
אבל יש בה ידיעה בסוף, al she-ein bah yediya lo betchila velo
besof veal she-ein bah yediya betchila aval yesh bah yediya besof, something
that was never known about, something that was known about... not known
at the beginning but known at the end, ועל טהור שאכל את
הטמא, ve-al tahor she-achal es ha-tamei, or a pure person that ate
טמא קרבן, korban שעיר הרגלים ושעיר ראשי חדשים ושעיר הנעשה בחוץ מכפרים.
sa'ir ha-regalim ve-sa'ir rashei chodashim ve-sa'ir ha-na'aseh bachutz mechaperim. So those all
do the same thing, they work on all three of them. Whether
it's ראש חודש, Rosh Chodesh. whether it's a רגל, regel, or whether
it is the goat that is done on the outside on יום
כיפור. Yom Kippur דברי רבי מאיר. Divrei Rabbi Meir. So he lists
all of those things. ואילו שעיר הנעשה בפנים שיירי. Ve-ilu sa'ir ha-na'aseh
bifnim shayrei. So but he doesn't say that that work is done
by the goat on the inside of יום כיפור. Yom Kippur? So
it's clear that the goat that is done on the Holy of
Holies of יום כיפור Yom Kippur does not do those... that job.
וכפרתן נמי שיירי, Ve-kapartan nami shayrei, and also the job that they're
doing, he never says is... done by the goat on the inside
of יום כפור. Yom Kippur. So it's very clear from this ברייתא
baraita that when רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir said they all do the
same thing, by all he meant all the מוספים Musafim do the
same thing, the one that's on the inside of יום כפור, Yom
Kippur, that continues to do its own job. Okay. Now we move
on to the question of even assuming they do separate things, which
is what רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon assumes, okay, that they do separate
things, they said to רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, 'Hey, רבי שמעון, Rabbi
Shimon, okay, so each one does a separate thing. If each one
does a separate thing, let's say you lost the goat here on
יום כפור מוסף Yom Kippur Musaf and you brought another goat for
it, and then you found the goat later. Could you go ahead
and bring it on סוכות? If you lost the goat on ראש
חודש, Rosh Chodesh could you go ahead and bring it on, you
know, פסח? So can you use one goat that was designated for
one of these to do for the to do for the other?'
And he said, 'Yes, you can,' he'll take off רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda for that. He said, 'Yes, you can.' So then they said,
'But wait a minute, if they all do something distinct, how can
you just exchange one for the other?' And he said, 'Well, yes
they're distinct but they're all the same genre. They're all טומאת מקדש.
Tumat Mikdash. And since they're all the same genre, you can go
ahead and if one is lost you can use it for it
you can and then found later you can use it for the
other one.' Presumably he would exclude the יום כפור בפנים. Yom Kippur
bifnim. I mean that's all part of pairing it, you know, with
the שעיר that's sent over the cliff and so on, although it
is true that here too, right, you know, it's it is טומאת
מקדש. Tumat Mikdash. Meaning I guess I would imagine that if you
lost one of these you couldn't use it for יום כפור בפנים.
Yom Kippur bifnim. But it's an interesting question if you lost the
goat that was supposed to be done for יום כפור בפנים Yom
Kippur bifnim and then you got a new one and you paired
it with the שעיר המשתלח se'ir hamishtaleach and then you found it
later, would you be able to use it for one of these?
Maybe? He says it's all the same genre, although again these are
also the same genre that they're מוסף. Musaf יום כפור בפנים Yom
Kippur bifnim is always a little separate.
Doesn't it get its content like right when you שחט shecht it?
Who cares what happens beforehand?
No, because it's sanctified as a particular type of a goat.
But you have that in mind specifically for, you know, meaning like,
I mean that's
a good question.
That is a good question. I mean but by יום כפור בפנים
Yom Kippur bifnim certainly. But like, can you just say 'I am
מקדיש makdish this as a חטאת, chatat. as a generic חטאת?' Why
not? Well, no. I mean look, when we're talking about you bringing
for your personal sin, we say that if you're מפריש mafrish something
for חטאת חלב chatat chelev and then you did another sin, you
can't use it for a different sin. Okay. So that means that
they are it's not generic חטאת. No, if you did a personal
sin, you can't I don't think you can say, I mean you
know if you did two sins you could say 'I'm מפריש mafrish
this for one of them, I'll decide which one later,' maybe. But
if you were did a sin you can't just מפריש mafrish it
generically. I think it has to be made specific. Or even if
it's maybe theoretically possible to do it generically, that wouldn't be the
standard case. The standard case is it's ראש חודש, Rosh Chodesh. we're
getting ready to bring the קרבן, Korban. we're being מקדיש makdish it
as the as the שעיר for ראש חודש. Rosh Chodesh So anyway,
but I don't know whether you could if you want.
Let's try to avoid the hypothetical.
Michael, how likely how often is it that you lose something? It's
right on ראש חודש, Rosh Chodesh we take the goat, this is
going to be our
מוסף, Musaf okay, or or חטאת. But it's an interesting question whether
in theory you could do it generically.
Yes. If they lost one, didn't they have to take a whole
new pair?
Yeah. But let's say that fine, they took a new pair, they
did what they needed to do on on יום כפור Yom Kippur
and then afterwards they found the one they lost. Can they now
use it for one of these? Right? So that would be the
question.
I remember that being the one who wasn't lost but wasn't chosen.
All right, that's a whole that's like you spend pages and pages
in מסכת יומא Masechet Yoma figuring that out. All right. So the
גמרא Gemara says like this: האי רבי שמעון אומר שעיר ראש חודש
מכפר על טהור שאכל טמא. Hai Rabi Shimon omer se'ir Rosh Chodesh
mechaper al tahor she'achal tamei. בשלמא דראש חודש לא מכפר אדרגלים. Bishlama
d'Rosh Chodesh lo mechaper ad'regalim. So before we get to the idea
that if you lose one you can designate it for something else,
we first want to clarify, we've clarified how we know each one
of these does its own thing or does a different thing. Now
what we're going to clarify and to a little bit we did
this already yesterday is how do we know now that we've designated
each one for something different that they don't that they only do
their own work and they don't work do the work of something
else as well. Okay. We did a little bit of this yesterday.
בשלמא דראש חודש לא מכפר אדרגלים. Bishlama d'Rosh Chodesh lo mechaper ad'regalim.
We know ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh doesn't do the stuff that the
רגלים regalim do. דאמר קרא עוון. De'amar kra avon. Because it says
by ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh עוון העדה, avon ha'eidah, if you remember
that. עוון אחד הוא נושא ואינו נושא שני עוונות. Avon echad hu
nosei ve'eino nosei shenei avonot. It only does one. So ראש חודש
Rosh Chodesh. only does its thing. It doesn't do some other
work. אלא דרגלים נכפרו אדרשי חדשים. Ela d'regalim nichparu ad'rashei chodashim. But
maybe something else like רגל, regel, maybe that should should do the
work also of ראש חודש. Rosh Chodesh ראש חודש rosh chodesh only
does one thing. But maybe the רגלים regalim can do two things.
נכפרו אדרשי חדשים. Nichparu ad'rashei chodashim. אמר קרא אותה. Amar kra otah.
It was given to you לשאת את עוון העדה laset et avon
ha'eidah by the ראש חודש. rosh chodesh אותה נושאת עוון. Otah noset
avon. Only the ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh does this job. ואין אחר
נושא עוון. Ve'ein acher noset avon. And nothing else does this job.
So now we know that the ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh
thing, I mean
that עוון, avon, that עוון, avon, the ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh only
does one job and nothing else does its job. So that way
now we know it doesn't it doesn't do the work of anything
else and nothing else does its work. So now we have to
figure out between these two. How do you know They don't do
the work of the other
one. בשלמא דרגלים לא מכפרים ידי יום הכיפורים, Bishlama d'regalim lo mechaperim
yedei Yom HaKippurim, I get the רגל regel doesn't do the work
of יום כיפור, Yom Kippur דאמר קרא אחת de'amar kra achat בשנה.
bashana. It says by יום כיפור, Yom Kippur this atonement is once
in the year, okay, which means that nothing else does the atonement
that the מוסף Musaf of יום כיפור Yom Kippur. does. כפרה זו
לא תהא אלא אחת בשנה. Kapara zo lo tehei ela achat bashana.
So the רגל regel can't do the work that יום כיפור yom
kippur does. אלא דיום הכיפורים נכפר אדרגלים, Ela de'Yom HaKippurim nechaper ad'regalim,
maybe maybe יום כיפור yom kippur should do the work for the
רגל? regel? Okay, אמר קרא אחת, amar kra achat, it says אחת
achat again. It says, what what does it say? Twice it says,
it says,
what's the פסוק pasuk it says? אחת
בשנה יכפר עליכם. Achat bashana yechaper aleichem. And here, I got to
quote the פסוק pasuk because I'm going to come up to it
in a minute. Is it 10:17?
I'm not sure.
No, it's not 10:17. והייתה זאת לכם לחוקת
עולם לכפר על בני ישראל מכל חטאתם
אחת בשנה. V'hiyata
zot lachem l'chukat olam l'chaper al bnei
Yisrael
mikol chatotam achat bashana. So this is all done אחת בשנה achat
bashana that it says at the very end of everything. And then
when it talks about the blood, it says, what does it say?
It says, וכלה מכפר את הקודש. V'chilah mechaper et hakodesh. Wait
a minute, where is it? Hold on.
I'm sorry, hold on one second. Hold on,
I don't know why I'm having a hard time finding it, I
apologize. It doesn't reference the exact פסוק. pasuk. וכיפר אהרן על קרנותיו
אחת בשנה. V'chiper Aharon al karnotav achat bashana.
Yeah, מדם חטאת
הכיפורים אחת בשנה יכפר עליו.
midam
chatat hakippurim achat bashana yechaper alav. That's in שמות.
Shemot.
Ah, that's why I can't find it. Okay, so in שמות Shemot
it says,
thank you, in שמות Shemot it
says, וכיפר אהרן, v'chiper Aharon, what is it?
על קרנותיו אחת בשנה.
al karnotav
achat ba-shana, What is it?
Yeah, it says twice אחת בשנה.
achat bashana. מדם חטאת הכיפורים אחת בשנה יכפר
עליו לדורותיכם קדש קדשים
הוא לה'.
Midam chatat hakippurim achat bashana yechaper alav l'doroteichem
kodesh
kodashim hu l'Hashem.
So it says אחת בשנה achat bashana. twice. So we basically explain
one of the אחת achat for saying that this only does one
job and not another job, okay, and that's how we know that
it doesn't do the work for the רגלים. regalim... And we know
the רגלים Regalim? doesn't do its work because it says אחת בשנה
achat bashana that what this does is only done once in the
year. Okay, fine. So now the גמרא Gemara continues, okay? ואינו מכפר
שתי כפרות. Ve'eino mechaper shtei kaparot. והא כי כתיבי אחת בשנה הנהו
דבפנים הוא דכתיבי. V'ha ki ketivi achat bashana hanahu d'bifnim hu de'chtivi.
So here it says, right, וכיפר על קרנותיו אחת בשנה מדם אחת
בשנה יכפר עליו, v'chiper al karnotav achat bashana midam achat bashana yechaper
alav, all of this is talking about what's done right, בפנים, bifnim.
by the מזבח הזהב, Mizbe'ach Hazahav, by the one that's done בפנים.
bifnim? So how can we use all those אחת achat to limit
the scope or to, you know, clarify the scope of these two,
since all the אחת achat are set up here by the one
that's done בפנים? הא כי כתיב אחת בשנה הנהו דבפנים
הוא דכתיבי. Ha ki ktiv achat bashana hanahu d'bifnim hu d'chtivi. אמר
קרא, מלבד חטאת הכיפורים. milvad chatat hakippurim. Okay, היקיש חיצון לפנימי, hishkish
chitzon l'pnim, because when it describes the outer one, it says לבד
חטאת הכיפורים, levad chatat hakippurim, you might remember that, and that's how
we learn that it did similar work. So the same way that
we learn it did similar work, we learn that the idea of
only doing one job and the job they do only being done
once, it says it here and it's also true here. Okay, so
the job done by the שעיר בפנים Seir bifnim is only does
one thing and nothing else does what it does. And because the
מוסף Musaf of יום כיפור is linked to the one on the
inside, also this only does one thing and nothing does anything else.
So the רגלים Regalim have to do something else. Each one of
these only does one thing and therefore this also only does one
thing.
Now, רבי שמעון יהודה משמו, Rabbi Shimon Yehuda mishmo, now רבי שמעון
Rabbi Shimon said in his name, in the name of his father,
רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, he
actually said the following: he said, the higher up you get on
this list, okay, the more it does. So this only does its
thing, but the רגלים... Regalim do both jobs, and the יום כיפור
here, I mean again, we're only talking within the מוסף Musaf world,
we're not talking, this is always doing its own unique thing, okay.
And the יום כיפור does all three jobs, alright? That's what רבי
שמעון Rabbi Shimon says in the name of his father רבי שמעון.
Rabbi Shimon. So now the גמרא Gemara says like this: מאי שנא
דראש חודשים דלא מכפר אדרגלים? Mai shna de-Rosh Chodashim de-lo mechapper a-de-Regalim?
Why does the ראש חודש according to him not do the work
of the רגלים? Regalim דאמר קרא: De-amar kra: עוון, Avon, עוון אחד
הוא נושא ואינו נושא שני עוונות. Avon echad hu nosei ve-eino nosei
shnei avonot. It only does one thing, not two things. של רגלים
נמי לא מכפר אדראש חודשים? Shel Regalim nami lo mechapper a-de-Rosh Chodashim?
So now, let the רגל Regel not do the work of the
ראש חודש. Now it's just going to go back and ask based
on the verses we laid out before. דאמר
קרא: De-amar kra: אותה, Osah, אותה הוא נושא עוון ואין אחר נושא
עוון. Osah hu nosei avon ve-ein acher nosei avon. It says, right,
ואותה נתן לכם ve-osah natan lachem by ראש חודש לשאת את עוון
העדה. laseit et avon ha-edah. So the same way עוון Avon says
that this only does one thing, אותה Osah should say nothing else
does its work. And that should say that these guys up here
don't do its work. ואותה Ve-osah should limit. So the גמרא gemara
says: אותה לא משמע ליה. Osah lo mashma lei.
Yeah, he doesn't, he doesn't think אותה Osah is saying that. End
of story. עוון Avon is saying it only does one thing. אותה
Osah is not preventing other things from doing its work. Okay, and
since they're all sort of, you know, associated, and remember by the
way, they're all in the same פרשה parsha
in פנחס, right? That's where we sort of all knew, you know,
that's let רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir say they all do exactly the
same thing. So this is like a variation of רבי מאיר. Rabbi
Meir. For רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir because all the מוספים musafim. are
together they do exactly the same thing. רבי
שמעון בן יהודה Rabbi Shimon ben Yehuda saying in the name of
רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon is saying that there is overlap, but they
don't do the same, all the same thing. Okay? This only does
its thing, but the stuff above it also does what it does.
And presumably that's because they're all in the same פרשה parsha of
the מוספים there in פנחס. And now we're going to go up.
The רגלים Regalim. the same, right? The רגלים Regalim does, goes down,
but it doesn't go up. Okay? So. Okay. מאי שנא דרגלים דלא
מכפר אדיום
הכפורים?
Mai shna de-Regalim de-lo
mechapper a-de-Yom HaKippurim?
And how do you know, since they're all in the same פרשה,
parsha, the רגלים regalim doesn't do the work of מוסף of יום
כיפור? דאמר קרא: De-amar kra: אחת בשנה. achat bashana כפרה זו לא
תהא אלא אחת בשנה. Kappara zo lo tehei ela achat ba-shana. Like
we said before, once in a year. This is only what יום
כיפור does is only done once. אי הכי, Ie hachi, דיום כיפור
נמי לא מכפר אדרגלים? de-Yom Kippur nami lo mechapper a-de-Regalim? If that's
true, then if we're going to learn the אחת בשנה, achat ba-shana.
the יום כיפור shouldn't do the work of the רגלים. אחת כתיב,
Achat k'siv, כפרה אחת מכפר ואינו מכפר שתי כפרות. kappara achta mechapper
ve-eino mechapper shtei kapparot. And here you can't say, oh, we don't
do anything with the word אחת, achat, because you're already doing something
with the word אחת. achat. So the same word אחת achat that
we're going to use to say that nothing else does the work
of the יום כיפור מוסף, yom kippur musaf that same אחת achat
or the other אחת achat in the פסוק pasuk should tell us
that, should tell us that it only does one job and it
doesn't do two jobs. So how can we say the מוסף of
יום כיפור does everything else's work? Got it? Okay? אחת Achat should
be telling you, the two אחת achats should be telling you both
of those things. So the גמרא Gemara says: אחת לא משמע ליה.
Achat lo mashma lei. Nah,
he doesn't do anything with אחת. achat. Of course, he just did
something with אחת, achat, so we'll get back to this. One minute.
אמאי? Amai? Why would אחת achat not be, you know, he not
be impressed with the word אחת? achat? דכי כתיב אחת בעשייה שבפנים
כתיב. De-chi k'siv achat be-asiyah she-bifnim k'siv.
Yeah, because the אחת achat is really written up here, by the
one done on the inside. Okay? So if you're not going to
use the אחת achat with down here, you're back to the issue,
which is let the רגלים do the work of יום כיפור מוסף.
אחת Achat no longer is saying that it gets to be the
only one that does this. אי הכי, Ie hachi, דרגלים נמי מכפר
אדיום הכפורים? de-Regalim nami mechapper a-de-Yom HaKippurim? דכי כתיב אחת בעשייה שבפנים
כתיב. De-chi k'siv achat be-asiyah she-bifnim k'siv. Fine,
so the אחת achat is only going on the goat on the
inside by יום כיפור. So let, so it, so it's completely irrelevant.
So therefore, since it doesn't say, since it doesn't say that this
can't do any other work, it should also say that other things
are able to do what it does. Okay?
We're not going to use the אחת? achat? Fine. לעולם אחת משמע
ליה. Le-olam achat mashma lei.
Fine, go back on what we said. Okay,
I take it back. Fine, he does use the אחת. achat. Because
we said the אחת achats are linked. Okay, so if he's going
to use the אחת, achat, you're back to the question that tells
you why nothing else can do what it does, it's the only
one that does what it does. But then you should also say
that it only does one thing. Why don't you say it only
does one thing? דשאני הכא דאמר קרא וכיפר
על קרנותיו אחת בשנה.
De-shani hacha de-amar kra ve-chipper al karnotav
achat ba-shana. קרנותיו דמזבח הפנימי הוא דכפרה אחת מכפר ואינו מכפר שתי
כפרות.
Karnotav de-mizbe'ach hap'nimi hu de-kappara achta mechapper ve-eino mechapper
shtei kapparot. Because the פסוק pasuk here, על קרנותיו אחת בשנה, al
karnotav achas bashana. is what we are saying is, is that the
idea here that only one, that you know, it can only do
one thing, it can't do multiple things. Okay, we're saying this אחת
בשנה achat ba-shana, says, because this אחת בשנה achat ba-shana doesn't mention
the מזבח. mizbe'ach. Okay, I mean it sort of does because it's
מכפר עליו, mechapper alav, but it doesn't mention it in direct juxtaposition.
Okay, so this אחת בשנה achat ba-shana is basically saying like this
atonement that's being done is only being done once. Okay, so nothing
else
But the idea that that it can't do something else is here,
right, is here being linked very much to על קרנותיו al karnotav
אחת בשנה. achat ba-shana That the stuff of the מזבח, mizbayach, of
the מזבח הפנימי, mizbayach hapnimi, right, that stuff, you know, that cleansing,
you know, what was I going to say, that is only cleansing
the מזבח הפנימי mizbayach hapnimi and doing nothing else. Okay, but that
is just particularly linked to the מזבח הפנימי. mizbayach hapnimi. Basically what
we're saying here is that because this says על קרנותיו, al karnotav,
this part is only goes on the שעיר הנעשה בפנים. sa'ir hana'aseh
bifnim. So for this שעיר הנעשה בפנים sa'ir hana'aseh bifnim we're saying
it does one thing and it doesn't do anything else. It cleanses
the מזבח הפנימי mizbayach hapnimi and it doesn't do anything else. But
this is a little more generic and therefore we can use one
of the אחת achas without using the other one.
Wait, wait, so what's the other אחת בשנה achas bashana used for
then?
This is saying, this one is saying,
this one is saying, this is the פנימי pnimiy and this is
saying only one job. Okay, so so it only does the
cleansing of the מקדש, mikdash, it doesn't do anything else. That only
applies to the פנימי. pnimiy. So here the יום כיפור מוסף doesn't
have that אחת. achas. So the יום כיפור מוסף can do the
job of other things, it can do down here these jobs. Okay,
but this is going by both aspects of יום כיפור and it's
saying what gets done on יום כיפור doesn't get done any other
times during the year. Okay? So you don't need another אחת בשנה.
achas bashana.
Right. In the first אחת achas up here, this has two אחת
achas and this only has one אחת. achas. Okay? And that one
אחת achas says nothing else does its job, it's the only thing
that does its job, but it can do other things' jobs. All
right? So just a way of limiting the אחת achas to the
inner goat. All right? Okay,
so let's read that. דאמר קרא וכפר על קרנותיו אחת בשנה, de'amar
kra vechiper al karnotav achas bashana, קרנותיו דמזבח הפנימי הוא דקאמר, karnotav
demizbayach hapnimi hu deka'amar, דלא מהני ליה אלא כפרה אחת, delo mahni
leh ela kapara achas,
it's the stuff of the inner altar that only does one job
and not two jobs. הא דחיצון, ha dechitzon, אפילו שתי כפרות, afilu
shtei kaparot, even does two jobs. And now we can all take
a deep breath because we are finally done with work it out
this whole chart. Okay, how do you know which one of these
things does? Okay, you got רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda that says רגלים
that, that you know, that basically puts ראש חודש up here. You
have רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon that makes ראש חודש a separate line
and says it also does the קרבן תמיד. korban tamid. You have
רבי מאיר's Rabbi Meir's idea that they all do the same thing.
You have רבי שמעון ורבי יהודה's Rabbi Shimon ve'Rabbi Yehuda's idea that
says the highest things do the work of a lower but not
the reverse. We got all the possibilities and now we're basically done.
Okay, I mean what we still haven't addressed is the question about
if you lose the goat can you use it for a different
one because they're all somewhat in the same פרשה. parsha. But now,
I feel bad that Michael left, well I don't know, I guess
Michael likes everything equally, but we're finally now going to move to
something which is a little bit more of a classic הלכה halakha
discussion now that we've mapped out all the פסוקים. psukim. So let's
take a look.
Well, that's actually an interesting point. This is more of a philosophical,
metaphysical discussion of הלכה halakha discussion because we're still required to do
this goat for this and so forth.
Right, but that's an interesting point. Like why does any of this
matter הלכה? halakha? But I mean it does matter to cause to
some degree it could impact the פרשה parsha question that we're asking
if you lose a goat from one can you use it for
the other and so on. But you're right. I mean to some
degree it's like, or
you run out of goats.
Yeah, but to some degree you're right. Like if people are being
atoned for, they're being atoned for, like you know, these קרבנות korbanot
are being brought regardless, like what difference does any of this make?
You know, which is a good question. All right, so now the
גמרא says like this. Now we're going to start on what seems
to be a totally new topic but we're going to circle back
to issues that are of relevance to us. אמר עולא אמר רבי
יוחנן, amar ulla amar rabbi yochanan, תמידים שלא הוצרכו לציבור נפדים תמימים.
tmidim shelo hutzrechu litzibur nifdim tmimim. So here's what happens. You've got,
you know, every year you take a new, you know, you do
a new תרומת הלשכה. trumat halishka. Everybody has to give their, you
know, מחצית השקל machatzis hashekel or whatever it is, and you use
all the new monies to buy new קרבנות korbanot because based on
the פסוק pasuk which is עולת חודש בחדשו, olas chodesh bechodsho, which
sounds like every month is new, but we say when the year
is נתחדש, nitchadesh, then you should use new money. New money. So
the קרבנות korbanot of each year have to be brought from monies
that were levied for that year and the year starts on ניסן.
nissan. Okay, so that's why by אדר, adar, you know, you start
to whatever, you know, or even before אדר, adar, whatever, you start
setting up people, you start collecting the money, and when ראש חודש
ניסן rosh chodesh nissan rolls around, you don't have all the money
in yet, you know, some people file their taxes late, but you
got enough of the money in that you start bringing the new
קרבנות korbanot with the new monies and then more money comes in
and then you whatever. Okay, so that's basically what happens. Starting ראש
חודש ניסן rosh chodesh nissan you need to bring the קרבן Korban.
with money that was levied for the
new year. defined as ראש חודש ניסן. Rosh Chodesh Nissan. Now, here's
what would happen though. Leading up to ראש חודש ניסן, Rosh Chodesh
Nissan, it's a day before ראש חודש ניסן, Rosh Chodesh Nissan, we're
bringing, you know, the two תמידים temidim that we bring every day,
you know, you bring these two sheep, right, one in the morning
and one in the afternoon. All right, that money that was bought
with last year's, you know, which is the last day of this
current year, you know, the last year's moneys. Okay, but the only
problem is that there's a הלכה halacha that they required that in
the chamber where they kept the lambs, that
there would always be six lambs. Okay, the reason for that would
be, the logic for that would be that you're supposed to have
a קרבן under your supervision for four days before you bring it.
Okay, so basically, you know, to make sure that it doesn't have
any blemishes. Okay, so if we have six lambs here, we're bringing
two today. Okay, so I got rid of the two I'm bringing
today, I'm bringing in two more. Okay, these two more, let's say
today is Sunday. These two more I brought in on Sunday. Okay,
today is Sunday
and those are the two new ones. Okay, it's Sunday. And I
brought these two on the altar. They're being brought on the
altar. Okay, fine. Okay, took two and I brought in two more.
It's Sunday. Okay, these get used on Monday,
these get used on Tuesday, these get used on Wednesday. So since
these are used on Wednesday, I've been having them under my supervision
Sunday, Monday, Tuesday, Wednesday, and you count the day itself. So that
means that I've been having them under my supervision for four days
and making sure that they don't have blemishes. That's by the way,
they use that idea as a metaphor for why we start saying
סליחות, sleichos, right, four days before ראש השנה, like you have to
check yourself for blemishes a minimum of four days and so on.
Okay,
so now here's what happened. This day Sunday I brought these two
on the altar. I haven't replaced them yet. Okay,
but it's the last day before ראש חודש ניסן. Rosh Chodesh Nissan.
These four are all bought with last year's moneys. I can't bring
them starting tomorrow. I can't bring these four which were bought from
last year's moneys. What do I do with them? They're completely unblemished,
they're sanctified, but now I'm not allowed to bring them. Yes, Charlie.
There's another problem. You bring the קרבן תמיד korban tamid for the
morning
and it's the 30th of אדר Adar and then witnesses arrive.
Let's not go there. All right, it's not relevant for us. Okay,
so it says like this.
But
what if you don't know what day ראש חודש is?
Doesn't matter, you always bring the תמידים, temidim, doesn't matter whether it's
ראש חודש or not. ראש חודש only affects the מוספים.
But it's last year's תמיד. tamid.
Oh, I see your point. Your point is that if it turns
out, then you brought it with the wrong moneys. Oh, that's, oh,
I wasn't hearing where you were going. That's an interesting question. I
don't know what you would do with that. Okay, אמר עולא אמר
רבי יוחנן, Amar Ulla Amar Rabbi Yochanan, תמידים שלא הוצרכו לציבור, temidim
shelo hutzrechu litzibbur, so those תמידים temidim you now don't need them
anymore because they're now last year's, נפדין תמימים, niftin temimim, you can
redeem them even though they're unblemished. Normally you're not allowed to redeem
something without a blemish, but you can't use these and you know
it wouldn't apply by a personal קרבן, but the sense is that
they're, you know, because it's a communal קרבן maybe you have a
little bit more latitude. Also of course the thing that you should
be thinking is you could have anticipated this, so maybe that should
feed into giving you a little more latitude because it was always
understood that these weren't going to, that four out of these weren't
going to be used. Okay, but anyway, that allows you to redeem
them, take their value, put that value on money. Okay, now these
sheep basically you know whatever they're not sanctified anymore. And now you
can take the new moneys and
transfer the sanctity on. So now you've got these four sheep, okay,
these four sheep here, you know you took out this money, okay,
and you transferred the sanctity on it. These four sheep are now
not sanctified. Then you take this money which is you know new
year, the new year's money and has the sanctity right and that
was raised for the purpose of buying קרבנות and so on and
that has sanctity because it was given to the בית המקדש Beis
HaMikdash and you basically transfer the sanctity of the new money onto
this and now these sheep are sheep for the new year because
they were bought, I mean they weren't bought, they were owned, but
the sanctity of the money that was raised was now transferred to
them and they're now in this new year's sheep. Then you can
use this money to do other stuff. Of course what you would
also want to know is what do I do with the money
that the old sanctity transferred to? So there's special הלכות halachos about
what do you do with like last year's money that's just סתם
stam say some extra money left over from last year, what do
you do with it? So this becomes last year's money and there's
things you can do with that, okay, and then this is now
bought with new year's money and therefore it allows them to be
brought now during this new year. Okay, so that's what he says.
But the חידוש chidush is... you can redeem it even without a
blemish, okay? נפשט כמימים? Nifshat k'mamin?
So יתיב רבה וקאמר לה להאי שמעתא. Yisiv Rabba v'kamar leh l'hai
shamata. So Rabba was sitting and telling over this discussion. אמר ליה
רב חסדא לרבה, Amar leh Rav Chisda l'Rabba, מאן צאית לך Man
tzait lach ולרבי יוחנן רבך? u'l-Rabbi Yochanan rabach?
Who do you think is going to listen to you and ולרבי
יוחנן רבך, u'l-Rabbi Yochanan rabach, your רבי? Rebbe? This what a crazy
idea that you can redeem a קרבן without a blemish ולרבי יוחנן
רבך. u'l-Rabbi Yochanan rabach. וכי קדושה שבהן להיכן הלכה? Vechi kedusha she-bahen
l'heichan halcha?
Where did their קדושה kedusha disappear to? Now of course the answer
is it disappeared because I redeemed it. But his point is you're
not allowed to redeem something without a blemish. Not that you're not
allowed, it doesn't work to redeem something without a blemish. The idea
of redeeming is only as operative when something has a blemish. That
allows the קדושה kedusha to be removed and to be put on
something else. When there's no blemish, that קדושה kedusha can't be removed.
And that's just the mechanics of it. So how did you manage
to do that?
So אמר ליה amar leh he said back to him, ואת לא
תשבור דאמינא V'at lo tishbar d'lamina קדושה שבהן להיכן הלכה? kedusha she-bahen
l'heichan halcha? Don't you agree that we're not concerned with this idea
of how do you get the קדושה kedusha to get removed? I'll
show you that we do get the קדושה kedusha to be removed
in a case that you agreed with. ותנן: V'tenan: מותר הקטורת Motar
haktoret מה היו עושין בה? mah hayu osin bah?
Let's say not the sheep, but it's the end of the year,
it's about to be ראש חודש ניסן, Rosh Chodesh Nissan, and you
bought at the beginning of the year a certain amount of frankincense
or whatever to make the קטורת, ktoret, and there's a whole long
תוספות Tosafos figures out exactly how much you buy and how much
you'll have leftover. Anyway comes the end of the year and you
have a certain amount leftover, okay, of all this קטורת ktoret that
you bought to be good use for the whole year. Now, same
problem. You can't use last year's קטורת ktoret for the new year.
Okay, so what do you do with it? It's exactly our issue
except that it's dealing with the קטורת ktoret instead of with the
sheep. So מפרישים ממנו שכר האומנים Mafrishim mimenu s'char ha'umanim ומחללין אותה
על מעות האומנים u'mechallelin osah al maos ha'umanim ונותנים אותה לאומנים בשכרן.
v'nosnin osah l'umanim b'scharan.
So this gets a little complicated, okay,
but basically the way it works is the following: is that that
you basically do like this. You have the
here
here are the כהנים Kohanim that work on the קטורת. ktoret. By
the way, they found that house, right? Didn't they found the house
that was the burnt house of the כהנים Kohanim who worked on
the קטורת? ktoret? I don't I think they might have found some
archaeological anyway, there was a group, a family of כהנים Kohanim that
worked on the קטורת. ktoret. But anyway and they did work for
the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, okay, and they were got paid for
their work, right? Other כהנים Kohanim who didn't have to do it
didn't have to work didn't have to, so even though you're a
כהן, Kohen, you got paid for your work, okay, for doing the
work on the קטורת. ktoret. So they would now here you've got
the leftover קטורת, ktoret, okay, from last year that has this קדושה.
kedusha. Here you've got the money that you are planning on paying
the כהנים Kohanim with. All right? All right that you would pay
the כהנים Kohanim for their job. Now, the problem is that that
money is קדוש kadosh as well. The money the קדושה kedusha goes
off that money because that money was raised for בית המקדש Beis
Hamikdash purposes. So what good does it do me to get paid
with sanctified holy money, I can't use it. But once I get
paid, the act of the fact that it's paying me for my
labor, it's a very fascinating idea, the קדושה kedusha of the money
transfers to the abstract labor. So if I basically took I don't
know like let's say it's not קטורת, ktoret, let's say it's a
piece of wood, okay? I took some metal and I made it
into this thermos because it was for the use of the בית
המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, they really needed a good thermos, okay? And I
now did ten dollars worth of labor. You pay me ten dollars
with sanctified funds, okay, and the קדושה kedusha of that thing goes
into the increased value like of this thing. All right, so an
interesting idea, right? But anyways so the קדושה kedusha goes to the
labor they've done. So the way רש"י Rashi explains it, תוספות Tosafos
has a different discussion, but anyway, you take this money, you either
give it to the כהנים Kohanim or you give it to somebody
here who's working in the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash who takes possession
of it for the כהנים. Kohanim. And then with the כהנים'ס Kohanim's
agreement, because now it's their money, it's their money and it's not
sanctified, with their agreement you transfer the קדושה kedusha onto this money.
Okay, now they're stuck again, what are they going to do with
money that's holy? But now what you do is you say, 'I'm
going now we have unsanctified קטורת, ktoret, okay, and
now we're going to pay you for your job, here's קדושה.' kedusha.
That's step number one, okay? Now we're going to pay you for
your job with all of this good קטורת, ktoret, okay?
Now what we're going to do is we're going to take some
money here from the new year and we are going to buy
that קטורת ktoret back from you, okay, with the new money. Since
we're buying the קטורת ktoret back from you with the new money,
the קדושה kedusha from this from the new money goes onto goes
onto
the קטורת, ktoret, right? You got that? Yep. And you, the כהן,
Kohen, now get that money. okay,
that's now חולין Chullin because it's because the קדושה Kedusha transferred. So
now we have קטורת Ketoret that's new year's קטורת, Ketoret, and you
got the money you need, but now we've got over here we've
got some we've got some money with the old קדושה Kedusha which
we'll have to figure out we'll go and do something else with.
Now that seems a little overly complicated and תוספות Tosafos asks why
aren't there easier ways to do it? But right now we're not
going to worry why there aren't easier ways to do it.
You can do that with animals too.
Whatever, that doesn't matter. You get the basic idea. The basic idea
though is that step number one we transfer the קדושה Kedusha away,
even though this is something that is fit to be used on
the מזבח. Mizbeach. How are you able to transfer the קדושה Kedusha
away? Where did the קדושה Kedusha disappear to? It's just like an
unblemished קרבן. Okay, וחזרו ולוקחין אותה מתרומה חדשה ve'chazru ve'lokchin otah mitrumah
chadashah and then you buy it back from the כהנים Kohanim with
the new money. ואמאי, Ve'amai, why is that true? נמי קדושה שבה
להיכן הלכה Namei kedusha shebah lehichan halachah and where did the קדושה
Kedusha disappear to? אמר ליה Amar leh קטורת קאמרת? Ketoret ka'amrat? Wait,
you're asking me about the
קטורת? Ketoret? שאני קטורת דקדושת דמים הוא. Shani ketoret dekedushat damim hu.
The קטורת Ketoret is not קדושת הגוף, Kedushat Haguf, it's קדושת דמים.
Kedushat Damim. Now here is a big difference, okay, that you have
to know, which is the basic, it's a very, once you understand
it, it's a very simple conceptual difference. קדושת דמים Kedushat Damim means
it is holy because essentially it's owned by the בית המקדש. Beis
Hamikdash. It's a question of ownership. And it's sort of like you
know they say that a cynic, what's they say a cynic is?
Somebody who knows, what is it? It's the cost of everything and
the value of nothing. So קדושת דמים Kedushat Damim just knows the
cost of something. It looks at something and all it sees is
dollar signs. Okay, this could be the world's most gorgeous cow or
the world's most beautiful car or whatever the heck it is, it
doesn't matter. Its only relationship to the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, קדושת
דמים Kedushat Damim conceptually is its value, its cost. We care about
this because this is an asset. Okay, that's what קדושת דמים Kedushat
Damim essentially is. Okay, קדושת הגוף Kedushat Haguf is something that we
care about the thing itself. קדושת הגוף Kedushat Haguf is something that
is it itself is going to do some function in the בית
המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. So the most obvious example is a קרבן. It
would also be קטורת Ketoret because you're going to burn it in
the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. We'll get to that. It could even
be wood that you are going to build into as a construction
material. Okay, but it is something that you are going to use
the thing itself. It's not just about
its dollar
value. It's fine. So that's the basic difference. Now, why does that
make a difference when you can redeem it? Because since קדושת דמים
Kedushat Damim is all about liquidating it into hard cash dollars,
so of course you can redeem it without a blemish. Who needs
a blemish? The whole point when I go ahead and I'm going
to do a fundraiser and you're all going to give me all
of thousands of dollars of donations and some of you are going
to give me cash and some of you are going to give
me your old cars or whatever, all of that is קדושת דמים.
Kedushat Damim. The only purpose of all of that is to turn
it into dollars. So of course I can go ahead and sell
it and get the money and so on. קדושת דמים Kedushat Damim
does not need a blemish. The whole point is you sell it.
Because it's
because the thing itself since it's owned by the בית המקדש, Beis
Hamikdash, if you were to now use it for your own personal
use, it would be מעילה. Me'ilah. It wouldn't just be stealing. Now,
you're right, you could in theory understand that things they own that
they're not going to use is just their property and you'd steal
it and nothing else. But because it is owned by the בית
המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, it has sanctity to it also. Before I've given
it to the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, if I say I am
sanctifying my car to as a donation, right, it's not just I'm
promising to give it. Right now it's automatically when those words come
out of my mouth owned by the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash and
not only owned, it has that sanctity status. It is a status
of the object. So you're right, it's different than secular ownership because
it's associated with the מקדש. Mikdash. It gets effected through my words
and it becomes owned and it affects its status. Now, so that's
why there you don't need a blemish. But something that I care
about the thing itself, I want to use this sheep on the
altar, I want to use this קטורת Ketoret on the altar. Okay,
so therefore, and I sanctified it so that it itself should be
used. So you can't change its status and make something that's about
to be that its identity is to be used on the מזבח
Mizbeach to go ahead and just magically make that identity go away.
You can only make that identity go away if it's got a
blemish and now can't be used anymore. Because it can't be used
anymore that allows you to remove its status and apply it to
something else. Okay, but as long as it's still fit to be
used, if this is all about what its identity is about, how
do you make that go away? That's the question of קדושה להיכן
הלכה. kedusha lehichan halachah. Now his answer that קטורת Ketoret is קדושת
דמים kedushat damim is the strange answer because קטורת Ketoret is itself
going to be used on the altar. But as we're about to
see, he doesn't mean it remains קדושת דמים. Kedushas damim. What it
means is that it requires a certain stage to give it its
intrinsic sanctity. Okay, because if you think about it, right, it goes
through a process, it gets pounded and, you know, and made into
קטורת Ketoret and then maybe it gets put into one of the
holy vessels in the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, a כלי שרת, Kli
shares, and the question is when does it get its קדושת הגוף?
Kedushas haguf? It could be that it starts as like a donation,
but because it can't be used in the state that it's given,
right? An animal, you can use it and slaughter it, it can
be used right away, okay, although the blood only gets thrown after
the animal, sort of whatever, but okay. But this, you know, but
at least the slaughtering is part of the עבודה avoda that you're
doing in the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. When I first give you
these, whatever plant or whatever you make the frankincense from, it can't
be used right away. So it starts as a donation, but then
as it gets processed and with holy vessels and gets fit to
be used, now we can say it has קדושת הגוף, Kedushas haguf,
because now the thing itself could be used. So his answer was:
I think at this stage, which is interesting because this is even
after it's been pounded and created, okay, but nevertheless, since it was
part of a process, it is not yet קדושת הגוף, Kedushas haguf,
and that's why you can do all of this. It will only
become קדושת הגוף, Kedushas haguf, we're going to see, when you put
it in one of the special temples and you're ready to offer
it—special vessels—כלי שרת, Kli shares, and you're ready to offer it up.
Until that moment that you're ready to offer it up and you've
put it in a special vessel, a כלי שרת, Kli shares, it
is still just in the process, it's not yet ready. And because
it's not yet ready, it's only קדושת דמים. Kedushas damim. But an
animal is immediately ready. You just slaughter it. And therefore I have
my problem with my animal, I don't have my problem with my
קטורת. Ketoret. Yes?
But since the animal needs the four days of being watched, doesn't
it have that
same—That's true, but it's not changing the object itself, you know? So
it's not seen—but it is an interesting question, and since asked a
question like what would happen בדיעבד bediavad if you didn't have the
four days, presumably also you could use it, that's sort of like
a—probably not a בדיעבד bediavad requirement. But also, it's really also a
issue about also that it has to be transformed physically. Okay, so
let's just read the first line, we'll continue with this tomorrow. השתא
ניחא דקדושת דמים הוא. Hashta nicha dekedushas damim hu. Actually, that is
the first line. Okay, and now the גמרא's going to get into
a more complicated discussion of is it really קדושת דמים Kedushas damim
or קדושת הגוף, Kedushas haguf, or it obviously eventually becomes קדושת הגוף,
Kedushas haguf, but at what stage does it become קדושת הגוף? Kedushas
haguf? Okay, so we will find out more about that tomorrow.